Guide to the Black Student Alliance records, 1969-2019 UA.31.04.0003
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Black Student Alliance records
1969-2019
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Black Student Alliance
UA.31.04.0003
1 Linear Feet
387 Megabytes
The Afro-American Society (now the Black Student Alliance) was established at Duke University in 1967, four years after the first Black undergraduates were admitted. The Afro-American Society was a social and activist group created to support students as they dealt with the challenges of Black life at a previously segregated institution. Contains fliers, memoranda, correspondence, printed e-mail, minutes, newsletters, reports, charts, a scrapbook, printed materials, and electronic records pertaining to the activities of the Black Student Alliance (BSA) and related Black and African American student groups at Duke University from 1969-2019.
Access Restrictions
Access note. Contains electronic records that must be requested and accessed in our reading room. Contact Research Services with questions.
Provenance
The Black Student Alliance Records were received as gifts from 1977 to 2019.
Historical Note
The Afro-American Society (now the Black Student Alliance) was established at Duke University in 1967, four years after the first Black undergraduates were admitted. The Afro-American Society was a social and activist group created to support students as they dealt with the challenges of Black life at a previously segregated institution.
The Afro-American Society's first political statement was made at the Hope Valley Study-In on November 13, 1967. Thirty-five members of the Afro-American Society staged a day long study-in protest in the lobby of President Knight's office. The study-in denounced the use of segregated facilities by University organizations and the membership of key University officers, including President Knight, in the segregated Hope Valley Country Club. The 1960s continued to be a turbulent time for race relations at Duke University. On February 13, 1969, Afro-American Society students led a Black student takeover of the Allen Building to spark University action on the concerns of Black students. The Allen Building takeover brought attention to issues such as establishment of an Afro-American studies program, a Black cultural center, and increasing the number of Black faculty and students.
In 1971, the Afro-American Society was renamed the Association of African Students (The Association). In 1976, the Association assumed its present title, the Black Student Alliance (BSA). The BSA continued to provide a cultural base for Black students at the University, growing into a major student organization on campus.
In the 1980s, when Black enrollment began to decrease, the BSA joined forces with the Undergraduate Admissions Office to make Black recruitment a primary goal. The Black Student Alliance Invitational Weekend, held each spring, allows prospective students to visit the campus and get to know the Duke experience from a Black perspective. The Reggie Howard Memorial Scholarship honors the first Black student government president, who served during 1976. This scholarship is offered to freshman students who demonstrate academic achievement and leadership potential.
The BSA is an active voice on campus, continuing to encourage University administration to take action to meet the needs of Black students, and during national events of concern such as systematic police violence against people of color. As a student group BSA notes misrepresentation in the student paper the Duke Chronicle; presents race relation panels; protests environmental abuse; and promotes Black and Jewish student discussion. The BSA also sponsors and cosponsors events such as performances by The Black Dance troupe; Martin Luther King Jr. Day celebrations; Black History month events; and occasionally hosting on campus speakers such as Reverend Jesse Jackson. The Black Student Alliance also coordinates events for Duke University Black Alumni. Some of the publications of the Black Student Alliance have been Prometheus Black, Revelations, The Talking Drum, and The Grapevine.
Collection Overview
Contains fliers, memoranda, correspondence, printed e-mail, minutes, newsletters, reports, charts, a scrapbook, printed materials, and electronic records pertaining to the activities of the Black Student Alliance and related Black and African American student groups at Duke University from 1969-2019. Forms part of the University Archives at Duke University.
Related Material
Howard, Chris D. Keep your eyes on the prize: the black struggle for civic equality in Durham, North Carolina, 1954-1963M. 1983 [904 D877, 1983-HO].
Duke University. Office of the Vice President. Legacy, 1963-1993: Thirty Years of African-American students at Duke University, 1995 [378.756563 L496, 1995]
Kotelanski, Jorge. Prolonged and patient effort: the desegregation of Duke University, 1948-1963, 1990 [904 P964, 1990-KO]
Duke University. Afro-American Society. Weusi za weusi, 1970 [371.9796073 W544, 1970]
Asian Students Association Records, 1995-2005
University Archives, Duke University
Diya Records, 1992-2006
University Archives, Duke University
African American students -- North Carolina -- Durham; African Americans -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Political activity; African Americans -- North Carolina -- Durham -- History; Student participation in administration; African Americans -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Social conditions; African Americans -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Social life and customs; African Americans -- North Carolina -- History -- Archival resources; African Americans -- North Carolina -- Political activity; African American Greek letter societies; Black lives matter movement; College students, Black -- North Carolina; Duke University. Afro-American Society; Martin Luther King, Jr., Day; African American History Month; Mentoring; Duke University. Spectrum; Duke University. Black Student Alliance; Duke University. Student Government; Duke University -- Students -- Political activity; Duke University -- Students -- Societies, etc.; Duke University -- Students -- Social conditions; Duke University. Afro-American Society; Abele, Julian, 1881-1950
- Black Student Alliance Records, 1969-2006
  - African and African-American studies, 1979, 1990, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Afro-American Society materials, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Alpha Kappa Alpha, fliers, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Area colleges and universities, 1990-1998 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - ASDU and Young Trustees, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Association of African Students, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Beyond the Dream Symposium, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Black Cultural Center proposal, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Black Faculty, 1988-1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Black Gentleman's Club, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Black Women's Collective, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bouchet Society, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Campus Community Development, Race and Race Relations Speakers Series, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Central Committee (of the Black Student Alliance), minutes, agendas, memos, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Contact lists, 1991-1998 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Corresondence, 1979- / 1998- (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Duke Women of Color United, flier, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Gospel Choir, fliers, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Harding, Calvin: Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Hurston-James Society, mission statement draft, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Inter-Community Council, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Kappa Alpha Psi flier, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Karamu, flier, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Mary Lou Williams Center for Black Culture, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous writings on Black history, 1995-1998 and undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - National Black Family Empowerment Agenda, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Samuel DuBois Cook Society, 1998 Feb. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Sister to Sister and Brother to Brother discussion groups, flier, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Students of the Carribbean Association (SOCA), fliers, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Tobie Wilder, Duke Student Government Candidacy, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Printed Materials, 1970-2006; undated
  - Black graduation yearbooks, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Black graduation yearbooks, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Black graduation yearbooks, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Black graduation yearbooks, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Black graduation yearbooks, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Black graduation yearbooks, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Brochures, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Chronicle articles, 1976-1997 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Duke University Black Alumni Connection, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Fliers, circa 1970-1998 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - The Grapevine, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Preparation for the '80s: 10 Years Ahead or Behind?", speech given by William Harston, Jr., 1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Revelations (Black Student Alliance newsletter), 1993 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook, 2004-2005 (loose) (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Scope and Contents note
    Unbound scrapbook created by BSA, detailing the organization's activities during the 2004/2005 academic year. Includes copies of and reactions to Philip Kurian's "The Jews," information about campus race relations, stereotypes, and police discrimination, as well as minority recruitment weekend, social events, community outreach, and public service activities. Scrapbook was created electronically with scanned materials and digital images, then printed on a color laser printer -- no loose materials glued or mounted.
  - The Talking Drum, Vol. 1, issue 1, 1994 Nov. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - The Talking Drum, Vols. 1-2, 1994-1997 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - The Talking Drum, Vol. 1, Iss. 1-4, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - The Talking Drum, Vol. 2, Iss. 2-4, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - The Talking Drum, Vol. 3, Iss. 1-5, 2004-2005 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - The Talking Drum, Vol. 4, Iss. 1, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Accession UA2018-0016, 2010-2018
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access note. Contains electronic records that must be requested and accessed in our reading room. Contact Research Services with questions.
  Scope and Contents
  Includes documents and photographs from the Black Student Alliance (BSA) group.
  - Agendas, 2010; 2017; 4 items; 4 documents (MS Word); approximately 30 KB (Digital-materials UA.31.04.0003-SET-0001)
    Includes meeting agendas.
  - Correspondence and Administrative Materials, 2012-2017; 109 items; 109 documents (MS Word; MS Excel; PDF; PNG; HTML files); approximately 1.7 MB (Digital-materials UA.31.04.0003-SET-0001)
    Includes correspondence; sign up sheets; descriptions; and documents related to the BSA F.A.M. Mentorship program; the Accenture Partnership; Colors of Duke photo campaign; social media; reports; YT candidates; Black Love event; Real Talk event; a script for an original game show; Black Affinity Groups; and the Black Pan-hellenic Council. Also includes documents related to elections; officers; a BSA Fashion Show; agreements; an untitled document with netIDs; and a copy of a UNC TV documentary, "Far Fetched and Dear Bought" which includes Julian Abele.
  - Events, 2014-2018; 313 items; 313 documents (MS Word; MS Excel; PDF; PNG; HTML files); approximately 1.7 MB (Digital-materials UA.31.04.0003-SET-0001)
    Includes photographs, schedules, plans, flyers, and videos for events including #BlackLivesMatter: A Movement, Not A Moment; the Abele Awards; painting the "Free Expression" bridge/tunnel; Real Talk Run Sheet; KCamp; and Renaissance Noire.
  - Minutes, 2010-2011; 2013; 2016-2018; 57 items; 54 documents (MS Word); approximately 2 MB (Digital-materials UA.31.04.0003-SET-0001)
    Includes minutes and meeting notes from BSA executive and general meetings.
- Accession UA2019-0007
  - BSA Records, 2019; 3 items; 53 document files (MS Word, Excel, Compressed); approximately 1.8 MB (Digital-materials UA.31.04.0003-SET-0001)
    Includes donation correspondence for the Flint Child Health and Development Fund, and a BSA Presidential Report.
- Accession UA2020-0023, 2018-2019
  - BSA Agendas, 2019 August 8-October 23; 11 items; 11 document files (MS Word); approximately 16 MB (Digital-materials UA.31.04.0003-SET-0001)
    Includes meeting agendas for BSA Executive Board; Black Caucus; and Leadership Team.
  - BSA Black Caucus, photographs, 2019 September 18; 44 items; 44 image files (JPG); approximately 8 MB (Digital-materials UA.31.04.0003-SET-0001)
    Includes photographs from the BSA Black Caucus event.
  - BSA Campus Shoots, photographs, 2018-2019; 14 items; 14 image files (JPG); approximately 83 MB (Digital-materials UA.31.04.0003-SET-0001)
    Includes group photographs of Black students on locations on Duke campus.
  - BSA Constitution, circa 2019; 1 document file (MS Word); approximately 1 MB (Digital-materials UA.31.04.0003-SET-0001)
  - Flyers, circa 2019; 3 items; 3 document files (.PDF, .JPEG, .PNG); approximately 3 MB (Digital-materials UA.31.04.0003-SET-0001)
    Includes event and signage graphics.
  - Planning Committee Agendas, 2019 October; 2 items; 2 document files (MS Word); approximately 2 MB (Digital-materials UA.31.04.0003-SET-0001)
  - Stroll Show, photographs, 2019 October 19; 73 items; 73 image files (.JPG); approximately 274 MB (Digital-materials UA.31.04.0003-SET-0001)
    Includes photographs from the National Pan-Hellenic Council (NPHC) Stroll Show event.